Guide to the Barry Ulanov Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Barry Ulanov Papers,
1932-2003
[Bulk Dates: 1940-1993].
Ulanov, Barry
18.5 linear ft. (14 record cartons, 1 document box 1 flat box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#1484
5644162
This collection contains the papers of Barry Ulanov, a jazz critic and professor of English at Barnard College. The bulk of the papers relates to Ulanov’s Barnard years (1950-2000). Most of the material consists of book manuscripts, research files, course materials, and correspondence.
Biographical Note
Barry Ulanov (1918-2000) was a jazz critic, professor of English at Barnard College, and prolific writer. He wrote, edited, or translated nearly fifty books and over a thousand articles on a wide range of subjects. His interests included music, modern art, psychology, history, religion, and literature.
Ulanov was born in Manhattan on April 10, 1918 and attended Columbia University, where he took advantage of his proximity to Harlem to immerse himself in jazz music and culture. After receiving his BA in 1939, Ulanov worked as a jazz writer and edited the journal Metronome from 1943 to 1955. He shifted the focus of the journal to cover more jazz and be-bop music, particularly black musicians who had previously received little notice in the journal. From 1955 to 1958 he wrote for Down Beat and published several biographies of jazz musicians in the 1940s and 1950s.
In 1939, Ulanov married Joan Bel Geddes, who had been a student at Barnard during his years at Columbia. This marriage lasted 29 years and produced three children: Anne, Nicholas, and Katherine. In 1968, Ulanov married Ann Belford, with whom he later had a son, Alexander. Ann Belford Ulanov taught at Union Theological Seminary as Professor of Psychiatry and Religion.
Ulanov's interest in the connection between modern art and contemporary American culture led him to pursue a Ph.D. in English Literature at Columbia University, which he completed in 1955. In the meantime, he also became involved in architectural projects in Denver, Colorado and Long Island. He taught English Literature at Princeton University from 1951 to 1953, and then, from 1953 to 1988, at Barnard College. He was an adjunct professor of Religion at Columbia University and, after retiring from Barnard, he taught at Union Theological Seminary in the Department of Psychiatry and Religion. Ulanov lectured worldwide on a range of topics.
Ulanov converted to Catholicism in 1951 and became involved with the Catholic Renaissance Society. He was an active member of the Vatican II Council, where he advocated for the use of vernacular in the mass and amplified music in church. Ulanov lectured at a number of Catholic colleges and spoke at the International Eucharistic Congress with Pope John XXIII in Bombay in 1964. He wrote and edited numerous books and articles on religion and culture.
In his last twenty years, Ulanov wrote extensively on religion and psychology, publishing over ten books with his second wife, Ann Belford Ulanov. Until his death, they co-edited the Journal of Religion and Health. Ulanov died on April 30, 2000, at the age of 82.
Scope and Content
The collection contains professional and research files, manuscripts, and documents of Barry Ulanov. Subject files include mostly pamphlets, flyers, clippings and copies of newspapers and journals relating to Ulanov's research interests, both for specific book projects as well as more generally. Contained, too, are extensive materials related to Ulanov's Barnard courses, such as syllabi, reading lists, correspondence, and relevant course readings. These subject files are comprised of both those files created by Ulanov, and those created during processing. The papers also include many of Ulanov's original manuscripts and translations, particularly his works on history of religion and Jungian psychology, as well as manuscripts sent to him by colleagues and associates, such as Lionel Trilling. Also included within the collection is Ulanov's correspondence, primarily relating to his speaking and lecturing as part of his professorship at Barnard College. There is also a large amount of correspondence which reflects his extensive work for the Catholic Church, as both a lecturer for Church organizations and as president of the Catholic Renaissance Society.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Subject Files, 1932-2000
Subseries I.1: Subject Files Arranged by Ulanov, 1932-1990s
Subseries I.2: Subject Files, 1940s-20
Series II: Writings, 1955-1993
Subseries II.1: Writings and Translations by Barry Ulanov, 1950s-1990s
Subseries II.2: Writings by others, 1950s-1990s
Series III: Correspondence, 1940s-2000
Subjects
Barnard College.; Bernanos, Georges 1888-1948.; Ulanov, Barry.; Catholic church and philosophy--United States.; Catholicism--psychology.; Literature--20th century--History and criticism.; Imagination--religious aspects--Christianity.; Poetry--History and criticism--Theory, etc.; Psychoanalysis and religion.; Theology--Philosophy.; Theology--20th century.; Theology--Bibliography.; Theology, Doctrinal--History--Study and teaching.; Theology in literature.; Theology--Study and teaching--Catholic Church.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Files containing student grades are restricted.
Acquisition
Gift of Ann B. Ulanov 2005
Selected Related Material-- At Columbia
Ann Bedford Ulanov Papers
Burke Theological Library, Archives of Women in Theological Scholarship Project
- Series I: Subject Files, 1932-2000
  This series contains Ulanov’s research and personal subject files. The files comprise, primarily, clippings and copies of journals and newspapers, some of which have handwritten marginal notes, underlining, and edits. Also included are Ulanov’s personal documents, as well as correspondence and files relating to his family. The Barnard files contain papers, correspondence, letters of recommendation, and memos relating to Ulanov’s professorship at that College. Note that several of the Barnard files contain restricted items. As there was no discernable order, these files were arranged alphabetically during processing.
  - Subseries I.1: Subject Files Arranged by Ulanov, 1932-1990s
    This first and largest subseries consists of subject files created by Barry Ulanov, and contains personal, professional, and research related material. The majority of the folders were labeled by Ulanov, and these names were retained. A few unlabeled folders were titled during processing; the titles of these folders are in brackets.
    - [General], 1950s-1990s, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Academic World, 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aesthetics, 1958-86 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Esthetics, 1968-72 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ancient World, 1956-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Anthropology, 1970-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Architecture, 1959-1995, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 10 to 11)
    - Architecture, and City Planning, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Art, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Art and Architecture, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Association for American Achievements, 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Australia--Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - [Barnard--General], 1970s-1980s, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 17 to 19)
    - Barnard Course Materials
      - [General], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - [General--student grades], 1990s (Box 1, Folder 21)
        [Restricted until 2068]
      - English 44, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - English 58, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - English 59-60, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - English 83, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - English 84/97 undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - English 85, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - English 86, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Film and Word, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Grades, Incompletes, Absences, etc., 1970s (Box 1, Folder 30)
        [Restricted until 2059]
      - Joyce, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Medieval and Renaissance Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Myths and Symbols of Modernity, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - [Program in the Arts], 1970s (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Religion W3234y, 61, 62, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Romantic Agony; Literature under a dictatorship, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Barnard Miscellanea
      - Articles, etc., 1960s (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Barnard, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - B.U., 1960s-1980s, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 7 to 9)
      - B.U. Reviews, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Clippings, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 12 to 13)
      - Course Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - [General,1950s-1980s], (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 15 to 16)
      - Prentice Hall, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - [Parnes, Randy--Death], 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Recommendations, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Recommendations by Ulanov, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Song of Songs, 1950s-1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 2)
      - [Television Broadcast], 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Books and Book Collecting, 1940s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Christian Humanism, Historiography, 1950s-1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Cities, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - [Clippings--General], 1950s-1998, (4 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 8 to 11)
    - Dance, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Detective Story, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Drama, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 14 to 15)
    - Drama--Modern, 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Education, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Eliot, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - English, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Family, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 20 to 21)
    - Film, 1950s-1990s, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 22 to 24)
    - Food, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Friends, 1960s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Furniture, Framing, etc., 1970s (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Gardens and Gardening, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Greece, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - History, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hopkins, 1948-1970s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Household, 1960-1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Humor, 1950s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Interiors, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Joyce, 1959-1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Kitchens and Bathrooms, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Language, 1950s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Lectures; Letters, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Liquor, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Literature, 1950s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Literature and Criticism, 1950s-1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 17 to 18)
    - Literary Theory, 1950s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Literature, Theory and Criticism, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Literature
      - Modern, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - American, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 22 to 23)
      - English, 1950s-1990s, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 24 to 26)
      - French, 1950s-1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
      - German, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Italian, 1947-1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Oriental, 1950-1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Russian, 1953-1993, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 7 to 9)
      - Spanish, 1972-1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Marx and Marxism, 1959-1996, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Medieval Literary Theory, 1953-1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Middle Ages, 1944-1986, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 14 to 15)
    - Music, 1932-1991, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 16 to 18)
    - Nature, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - No Entrance, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Novel, The, 1957-1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Painting, 1958-1994 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Painting--Modern, 1940s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - [Papers and Correspondence], 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Philosophy, 1940s-1990s, (7 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Phonographs and Records, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Photography, 1960s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Pound, 1953-1962, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Poetry--Modern, 1950s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Poets--Recent American and English Poets, 1951-1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Politics, 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Politics--Marxism, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Psychology, 1958-1982 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Renaissance, 1958-1982 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Renaissance Art, 1946-1957 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Repairs and Refinishing, 1950s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Science, 1916-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 21 to 22)
    - Shakespeare, 1950s-1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 23 to 24)
    - Sociology, 1972-1986 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Sociology--Anthropology, 1974-1982 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Song of Solomon
      - [Cantique des Cantiques, Le], undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - Commentaries, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - English Verse, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - [Exposition, An], undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - [Oversized Research Materials], undated, (5 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1 to 5)
      - [Paraphrasis gemina], undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Paraphrasis poetica, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - [Research Materials], undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Select Hymns, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Solomon in Metre, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Solomon's Song Paraphrased, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Song of Solomon, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Song of Songs, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 10 to 11)
    - Style, 1950s-1960s (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Television and Radio, 1946-1963 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Theology, 1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Theology and Religion, 1957-1983 (Box 7, Folder 15 to 16)
    - Travel, 1970s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Two Cultures, The, 1950s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Typography, 1950s-1960s (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Witches, Clowns, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 20 to 21)
    - Witches and Clowns Pictures, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Women, 1970s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 23 to 24)
    - Zeitgeist, 1950s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Subseries I.2: Subject Files, 1940s-2000
    This additional subseries of subject files contains material from the Ulanov collection, arranged by subject, and created during processing. The material dates mostly from the 1950s to the 1990s and includes personal papers and contracts, handwritten notes, photographs, and pamphlets and published material relating to lectures and public appearances. This series contains material related to Ulanov’s work on the Roosevelt Field Shopping Center, Family Weekly, and the Catholic Renaissance Society.
    - Association for American Achievements, 1974 (oversize) (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Barnard, circa 1978 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Catholic Renaissance Society/Oesterreicher, 1955-1964 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Clippings Mentioning Ulanov, 1950s-1960s (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Family, 1950s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Family Weekly Reading List, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Jazz Material, 1950s-1990, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Jazz Material--Posters, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Maps and Views, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Pamphlets, 1950s-1990s, (4 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 8 to 11)
    - Personal Documents and Contracts, 1940s-1960s (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Photographs and Slides, 1960s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Publications with inscriptions to Ulanov, 1950s-1960s (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Research and Notes, undated, (4 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 15 to 18)
      (Handwritten and Notebooks)
    - Roosevelt Field Shopping Center, 1955-1956 (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Series II: Writings, 1955-1993
  The writings contained within the collection are both those of Ulanov and those written by others. Ulanov’s writings include transcripts/working notes for speeches and addresses, articles, and book manuscripts from the 1950s to the 1990s. Contracts, publisher correspondence, and other material related to writings have been filed with the appropriate manuscript. The material is arranged alphabetically.
  - Subseries II.1: Writings and Translations by Barry Ulanov, 1950s-1990s
    This subseries contains manuscripts of works by Ulanov: books (monographs and anthologies), translations, articles, and speeches from the 1950s through the 1990s. Most of the drafts have handwritten notes. Some folders also contain correspondence with publishers or co-editors related to that particular work. This subseries includes research notes for unpublished books, such as Man… from the Beginning and Analysis of Prose, as well as his PhD dissertation from 1955. Several folders contain printed copies of published material.
    - General Articles--undated, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 2)
    - General Articles--Published, 1950s-1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 27 to 28)
    - General Speeches-- 1960s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Analysis of Prose--Research Materials, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Anima/Animus (later Transforming Sexuality)
      - Draft with Notes, 1991, (5 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 4 to 8)
      - Draft, 1993, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 9 to 11)
      - Correspondence with Publishers--Footnotes, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Death: a Book of Preparation and Consolation
      - Draft, 1959, (7 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 13 to 19)
      - Draft, 1959, (6 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 6)
      - Clippings and Supplementary Materials, circa 1959 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Draft with Notes, circa 1959 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Education for Eternity," 1962 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Essay on the Middle Ages," undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - The Fashioning of Angels, undated--w/ AU. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - The Healing Imagination
      - Draft, circa 1991, (3 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 12 to 14)
    - "Inside Talk" in The Living Pulpit--with Notes, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Joy out of Sorrow
      - Original Version in French by Mother Marie des Douleurs--with Correspondence and Photos, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Draft of Translation--with Notes, 1958, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 11 to 12)
      - Draft of Translation--with Notes, 1958, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 13 to 14)
    - Jung and the Outside World
      - Handwritten Notes, 1990s (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Partial Draft, circa 1990 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Partial Draft, circa 1990, (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 3)
      - Partial Draft--Introduction by Ann Belford Ulanov, circa 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Draft, circa 1990, (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 5 to 7)
      - Draft, circa 1990, (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 8 to 10)
      - Draft, circa. 1990, (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 11 to 13)
      - Draft, circa. 1990, (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 14 to 16)
      - Partial Draft--with Handwritten Notes, circa 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 17 to 18)
    - Contracts and Correspondence, 1984-1992 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - The Last Essays of Georges Bernanos--Translator’s Note with Notes--Clippings, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "Leave Me Be"--Music by Billy Strayhorn, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Lennie Tristano: the New Tristano"-- Liner Notes, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - "Leon Battista Alberti, Idea and Reality"--PhD Dissertation, 1955, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 15 to 16)
    - Lunceford, Jimmie--Article Draft, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 17)
      (with Notes and Clippings)
    - Making of a Modern Saint
      - Draft, 1966, (4 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 18 to 21)
      - Drafts and Correspondence, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 22)
      - Notes and Clippings, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Man... from the Beginning
      - Orient Timelines, 1950s-1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 18 to 19)
      - Europe Timelines, 1950s-1960s, (4 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 20 to 23)
      - History Timelines--with Notes, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Painting Timelines, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - Timelines--with Notes, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Materials from Collier’s Encyclopedia, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Correspondence, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 28 to 29)
    - Modern Culture and the Arts
      - Draft with Notes, 1972 (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 24 to 25)
        (some correspondence)
      - Draft with Notes, 1972 (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Mysticism and Negative Presence" in The Journal of the Ancient Near Eastern Society of Columbia University, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Poetry Now
      - Research--with Notes, circa 1970s, (3 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 5 to 7)
      - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Prayers of Saint Augustine--Galley with Notes, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Religion and the Unconscious--Preface to the Korean Edition, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - The Recorded Music of W.A. Mozart, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - "The Rhetoric of Love"--Research Proposal, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - "Smooth Rough"--Transcript of Interview, 1966 (with notes) (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - "Six Authors in Search of a Character"--with Notes on Modern Drama, circa 1960s (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Sources and Resources
      - Partial Draft, circa 1959 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Partial Draft--with Notes, circa 1959 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Partial Draft--Chapters Thirteen and Fourteen, circa 1959 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Draft--with Notes, circa 1959, (6 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 18 to 23)
      - Page Proofs--with Correspondence from Publishers, 1959, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 24 to 25)
      - Index and Permissions--with Notes, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - Correspondence from Publishers, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - The Tell Tale Heart: An Opera in One Act--with Production Notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - "Therese and the Modern Temperament," undated (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - The Witch and the Clown
      - Partial Draft, circa 1987 (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - Draft, circa 1987, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 31 to 32)
    - Women: A collaboration of Artists and Writers, 1948 (oversize) (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II.2: Writings by Others, 1950s-1990s
    This subseries contains manuscripts sent to Ulanov by colleagues and friends. Some are translations are from French into English. There are several articles and books on religion. An undated article by Lionel Trilling and a translation of a play by Paul Claudel are included.
    - Anonymous--"The Fullness of Christmas," 1955 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Arnold--Untitled Book manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Claudel, Paul-- A Piece of Noon, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - [Colie, Rosalie L.]--Atlantic Wall, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Crowley, Father John-- Untitled Manuscript, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Elbert, Father John A-- An Approach to a Christian Philosophy of Science, with Correspondence, circa 1962 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - de Ghelderode, Michel--Barabbas, translated by Hugh Dickinson, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Giraudoux, Jean--No War in Troy, translated by Jean-Pierre Giraudoux and Betty Askwith, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Jones, Mira--"Psychic Reality," undated (with hand edits) (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Maidenbaum, Aryeh--"Psyche, Bible and Story," 1991 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Sister Miriam--Chapter 5 of Manuscript on Art, undated (with Correspondence) (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - [Murray, Albert]--"Duke Ellington’s Place in the National Pantheon," undated (Box 12, Folder 16)